ILGWU Local 22 Israel Breslow Papers 5780/067
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Local 22 Israel Breslow Papers
1913-1981
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Breslow, Israel
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/067
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection contains the records of Local 22's manager, Israel Breslow, including speeches and articles by Breslow, files relating to local union elections, and Breslow's reports to the membership.
6322178
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
B. Walker, September 26, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Israel Breslow (1906-1985) emigrated from the Ukraine to Canada where he worked in the garment industry and, from 1922 to 1936, was a member of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. In 1936, after moving to New York City and beginning work as an operator in the garment industry, Breslow joined Dressmakers Local 22. Breslow served on the local's executive board and as the local's business agent, and from 1958 to 1975, he served as manager. In 1962, Breslow became a vice president of the ILGWU. He retired from the ILGWU in 1975, after which he became president of the Jewish Daily Forward Association. Additionally, Breslow was president of the Workmen's Circle from 1958 to 1962, and again from 1966 to 1970.
Biographical / Historical
Local 22 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Dressmakers' Union, was chartered in December 1920 and based in New York City. The dress industry formed its own Joint Board in 1921 composed of Local 22 Dressmakers, Local 25 Waistmakers, Local 58 Waist Buttonhole Makers, Local 60 Waist and Dress Pressers, Local 66 Bonnaz Embroidery Workers, Local 89 Italian Waist and Dressmakers, and the waist and dress branch of Cutters' Local 10. A general work stoppage in February 1923 in the dress industry won the union a 40 hour week and 10 percent wage increase, as well as a large gain of new members. During the summer of 1923, after years of discussion and deliberation, the two dress locals, Local 23 and 22 were consolidated. The dressmakers from Local 23 transferred to Local 22 and subsequently Local 22 joined the New York Cloakmakers' Joint Board. Soon, the Dress and Waist Joint Board became unnecessary and was dissolved. Local 25 Waistmakers were left without an affiliated organization and in October 1924 merged with the Dressmakers' Union, Local 22.
By the end of 1926, the Communists had gained control of the dress organization in New York City and the union barely existed. In February 4, 1930, 25,000 dressmakers walked out of the shops. The strike was called to reorganize dressmakers and finally abolish the Communist influence in the industry. On April 8, 1930 the General Executive Board decided to separate the dressmakers from the Cloakmakers' Joint Board. In 1931, Charles Zimmerman formed a committee to rebuild Local 22. He was elected to executive board of Local 22 in 1932, and elected manager-secretary in 1933. Another walkout in all dress shops, both union and non-union on August 16, 1933 brought the dress industry to a halt.
Zimmerman left Local 22 in 1958 to become manager of the Dress Joint Board. Israel Breslow succeeded him as manager of Local 22 from 1958 until his retirement in 1975. By 1975, the New York Dress Joint Board completed restructuring of affiliate locals, and Locals 60-60A, 159, and 38 were merged into existing Locals 22 and 89. Local 22 gained jurisdiction over all dressmakers in Manhattan. In the 1980s, more locals were dissolved and members transferred to Local 22, but by 1984, Local 22 saw restructuring as well. Changes in the garment industry necessitated the dissolution of the Joint Board and Local 22 into the new Local 89-22-1.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the records of Local 22 manager Israel Breslow. Included are speeches given by and articles written by Breslow, much are which are in Yiddish. There are also letters and correspondence.
There are files relating to local union elections, including the Local 22 campaigns and accompanying election material, particularly as it relates to the Dressmakers Progressive Group led by Charles Zimmerman, their program and platform,
Additionally, there are agendas and notes for the Membership and Nominations meetings with brief reports. These provide information on the status of the dress industry.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/014: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Papers 5780/014 P: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Photographs 5780/015: ILGWU Local 22 Records 5780/036: ILGWU Local 22 Minutes 5780/057: ILGWU Local 22 Education Department Records 5780/057 P: ILGWU Local 22 Education Department Photographs
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Breslow, Israel; Lakatz, Moshe; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.)
6322178
- Notes for Speeches - Election Campaign, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Local 22 Seminar, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  May 5-12, 1973
- Speeches, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Articles, 1935-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters to the Union, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Israel Breslow and Moshe Lakatz Articles.... (title in Yiddish), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters, 1965-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1952 Campaign and Misc., 1947-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Yiddish Articles (no dates) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1956 Local 22 Campaign, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1950 Local 22 Elections, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 1953 Local 22 Elections, 1942-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Elections 1956 in ILGWU Locals, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 1956 Local 22 Elections, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 1965 Local 22 Elections, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Local 22 and The Morning Freiheit, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Membership Meetings Reports, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Managers' Reports to Membership Meetings, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Membership Meetings, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Local 22- Managers' Reports to General Membership Meetings, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Reports to Membership Meetings - I. Breslow's Notes, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Shop Chairman Card and Acquisition Note (Box 1, Folder 23)
- 1980 Convention - Includes Carter Speech (videocassette) (Box 2)
  [Removed to 5780 AV]
- WTOP Radio Coverage of ILGWU Chorus Rehearsal, 1977 (audiocassette) (Box 2)
- Horizons Series - NPR - "Battle in the Sweatshops", 1980 (audiocassette) (Box 2)
- Executive Board Minutes, 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Accounts Ledger, 1921-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Report on Cotrell and Leonard Boycott, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Leaflets, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Commendatory Letters 1950s and '60s, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photos, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Also undated.
- Negatives "Forward to ILGWU 50th Anniversary Supplement" (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Misc. Speeches, Articles, Leaflets, 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- International Labor Press Association Film and Broadcast Competition - Awards of Merit, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Education Department, 1933-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Legal Documents, 1928-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Songs and Scripts, 1940-1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)